<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-10T16:35:57+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Pola Schwöbel</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace, helvetica based portfolio theme.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">new paper</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="new paper" /><published>2020-07-10T11:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-07-10T11:26:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/10/title.html">&lt;p&gt;You can find “Probabilistic Spatial Transformers for Bayesian Data Augmentation” &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2004.03637.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You can find “Probabilistic Spatial Transformers for Bayesian Data Augmentation” here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">talk at AI expo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/20/title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="talk at AI expo" /><published>2019-10-20T14:11:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-20T14:11:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/20/title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/20/title.html">&lt;p&gt;Last month I was invited to give a talk at the AI Expo at &lt;a href=&quot;hhttps://www.skylab.dtu.dk&quot;&gt;Skylab&lt;/a&gt;, DTU’s lovely space for student innovation and entrepreneurship. I gave a quick overview over the field of Algorithmic Fairness and spoke a bit about my own research. The slides can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/img/Bias_in_bias_out.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/skylab.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
	200+ people showed up and asked a lot of smart questions after my talk. Thanks!
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Last month I was invited to give a talk at the AI Expo at Skylab, DTU’s lovely space for student innovation and entrepreneurship. I gave a quick overview over the field of Algorithmic Fairness and spoke a bit about my own research. The slides can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">summer school organization</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="summer school organization" /><published>2019-09-06T18:11:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-06T18:11:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/09/06/title.html">&lt;p&gt;My section holds a summer school on Advanced Topics in Machine Learning every year. For the first time it was organized by a PhD student - me! I chose the topic “Fairness and Machine Learning” and hosted the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.compute.dtu.dk/courses/02901/&quot;&gt; event&lt;/a&gt; at DTU from August 26th - 30th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithmic fairness is something I am interested in personally, and many more people are. A quite vibrant research field within computer science and ML in particular has emerged during the last 8 years or so. People are interested in measuring how “fair” algorithms are, for example by evaluating whether their decisions are equally advantageous for men and women, or whether the same prediction accuracy is achieved across different demographic groups. Once algorithmic bias is detected, researchers try to develop techniques to overcome it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring fairness in such a quantitative way is of course a hard thing to do. Fairness can mean different things depending on context, and some of the definitions contradict each other. While we as computer scientists cannot solve those societal questions, I find it very useful to try and operationalize some of our ideas of ethics and translate them into formulas and code, thereby making them accessible for the technical community to work with. Putting something into maths is also a really good way to force yourself to be precise about what exactly you mean when you say an algorithm is (un-)fair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our great speakers gave lectures and tutorials during the five course days. In the evening there were social events, e.g. a fantastic meetup where start up people talked about the implementation of the theoretical concepts we had been discussing. Super interesting week packed with smart people discussing difficult problems (and a lot of hard work pulling all the strings). Looking forward to next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/silvia_chiappa.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
	A bad picture of a great talk: Silvia Chiappa from Deepmind talking about Algorithmic Fairness and Causal Inference.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My section holds a summer school on Advanced Topics in Machine Learning every year. For the first time it was organized by a PhD student - me! I chose the topic “Fairness and Machine Learning” and hosted the event at DTU from August 26th - 30th.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">more firsts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/18/title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="more firsts" /><published>2019-06-18T21:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-18T21:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/18/title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/18/title.html">&lt;p&gt;The PhD school at DTU Compute organized a PhD Bazaar. It was a great opportunity to learn about everyone’s work and I feel lucky to be part this amazing group of young researchers. My own pitch was caught on  &lt;a href=&quot;https://video.dtu.dk/media/Pola+Schwöbel/0_1890tjat&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;img&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img class=&quot;col three&quot; src=&quot;/img/pitch.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;col three caption&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The PhD school at DTU Compute organized a PhD Bazaar. It was a great opportunity to learn about everyone’s work and I feel lucky to be part this amazing group of young researchers. My own pitch was caught on video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a lot of firsts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/title.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a lot of firsts" /><published>2019-06-17T19:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T19:53:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/title</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/06/17/title.html">&lt;p&gt;I finally made my website to collect some notes, thoughts and learnings from my PhD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that it’s become increasingly more important to market yourself as a young researcher (or, really, as a human being). While many of us are critical of this trend  - and rightfully so - I do think there is value in learning how to communicate your work. DTU puts a lot of focus on teaching us this kind of skills, and I am very grateful for their effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went ahead and made my own website! I used github.pages and the jekyll templating engine. The upsides: It’s free, and rather easy to do if you have some basic coding skills. It should also make it very easy to publish tutorials and all things code - we’ll see about this later. The downside: While there is templates out there to use, it probably won’t turn out quite as beautiful as with services like squarespace or cargo collective (at least not with my newly acquired and very mediocre web development hacker skills).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I finally made my website to collect some notes, thoughts and learnings from my PhD.</summary></entry></feed>